[{"question":"The date of commencement of the Indian Constitution is","choices":["26-11-1949","26-11-1945","26-01-1950","15-08-1947"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Preamble of Indian Constitution indicates","choices":["Privigileges given to SC & ST","The power of government to make laws","The circumstances under which the Constitution can be amended","The source of the Indian Constitution"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The source of authority of the Indian Constitution is","choices":["The Government","The people of India","The Supreme Court","The President"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"One of the objective of the Constitution is to achieve","choices":["Law and order","Justice","Political Stability","Social Control"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The word secular as used in the preamble indicates","choices":["Treating all the languages equally","Special treatment to Hindu religion","Treating all the religions equally","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The state whose executive head is elected representative is called","choices":["The Republic","Anarchy","Monarchy","Dictatorship"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The first written document with respect to basic rights is the","choices":["Magna Carta of England","Constitution of India","Constitution of America","French declaration of rights of man and citizen"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Fundamental Rights are protected by the","choices":["Civil Courts","Criminal Court","Supreme Court","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Fundamental Rights are","choices":["Civil Rights","Criminal Rights","Basic Rights","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Part-3 of the Constitution guarantees how many categories of Fundamental Rights","choices":["Five","Six","Seven","Eight"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The right to equality means","choices":["Treating all citizens equally","Treating government servant equally","Treating citizens differently","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Equality must be among","choices":["Equals","In-equal","All","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Article 14 permits reasonable","choices":["Classification","Discriminations","Division","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"State is prohibited from denying any citizens access to","choices":["Shops, Public Restaurants etc.","private places","Men & Women","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"State is authorized to make special provision for","choices":["Women & Children","Men only","Men & Women ","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"State can make special provisions for the advancement of","choices":["Socially and economically backward classes of citizens","Economically backward classes of citizens","Only socially backward classes of citizens","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Equality in public employment means","choices":["All applicants are entitled to be employed","State has to give equal opportunity in public employment without discrimination","State cannot prescribe any condition of employment","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"...........can be the ground for reservation of posts","choices":["Language","Residence ","Colour of the person","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Untouchability is","choices":["An offence","Not an offence","Permissible","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The Constitution provides for the abolition of","choices":["Titles","Salaries of public servants","Allowances of the members of the parliament","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The freedom of speech includes","choices":["Freedom of press","Freedom of disturbing public peace","Freedom to create nuisance","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Freedom of speech and expression means right to express one's own opinion only by","choices":["Words by mouth","Writing and printing","Both as mentioned above","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Freedom of speech includes","choices":["Freedom of silence","Freedom of insulting others","Both as mentioned above","None of these "],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Classification of films into 'A' & 'U' is","choices":["Valid","Invalid","Either of the mentioned above","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Freedom of assembly means right to assemble peacefully","choices":["With arms","Without arms","With deadly weapons","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Freedom of association includes","choices":["Freedom to move","Freedom to form companies","Freedom to reside & settle","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The freedom of movement under Article 19 (1) (d) can be restricted in the interest of","choices":["Women","Law & Order","General public","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Freedom of Residence means right to","choices":["Reside and settle only in a particular area","Reside and settle in any part of the territory of India","Reside in a foreign country","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Right to Property is a","choices":["Ordinary Right","Fundamental Right","Moral Right","Not a Right"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The Constitution guarantees Right to Practice","choices":["any profession, occupation, trade or business","Only profession","Both as mentioned above","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The Constitution guarantees  Fundamental rights to","choices":["Both citizens and Non-citizens","Citizens only","Foreigners only","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Ex-post facto law means","choices":["Law imposing penalties from a previous date","Law imposing penalties from a future date","Civil Law","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Double Jeopardy means","choices":["No prosecution and punishment for the same offence more than once","There can be prosecution and punishment for the same offence more than once","Double benefit","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Self-incrimination means","choices":["Compulsion to be a witness against himself","Compulsion to be a witness against others","Voluntarily gives evidence","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Article 21 protects","choices":["Life only","Liberty only","Life & Personal Liberty","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Right to life includes","choices":["Right to live with human dignity","Right to not live with human dignity","Right to mere animal existence","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Right to Shelter is part of","choices":["Right to live","Right to equality","Right to freedom","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"An arrested person has ____ number of rights under Article 22","choices":["4","5","1","6"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The first right under Article 22 is","choices":["Right to be informed of grounds of arrest","Right to consult his own lawyer","Right to be produced before a magistrate","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"An arrested person must be produced before a magistrate within ___ hours of his arrest","choices":["12","24","36","48"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Telephone tapping is violation of","choices":["Right to Freedom of Speech & Expression","Right to life and personal liberty","Right to carry on any profession","Right to equality"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"A person can be detained under Preventive Detention Law","choices":["If he has committed offences against the public","If he is likely to cause harm to public","If he is insolvent","If he is alien enemy"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Right to pollution free environment includes","choices":["Right to life","Freedom of Speech and Expression","Right to religion","Abolition of Untouchability"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Right to life includes","choices":["Prisoners Rights","Teachers Right","Students Rights","Ministers Rights"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Right to Education is a","choices":["Fundamental Rights","Ordinary legal Right","Not a Right","Both as mentioned above"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Traffic in human beings & labour is","choices":["Prohibited under the Constitution","Permitted under the Constitution","Both as mentioned above","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Children below the age of ___ years are prohibited to be employed in hazardous employment","choices":["21 years","18 years","14 years","30 years"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Right to Freedom of Religion aims at achieving the concept of","choices":["Secularism","Federalism","Political justice","Economic justice"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"There can be prohibition of religious instruction is _____ institutions","choices":["State aided","Unaided","Minority Educational","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The tax collected by the state cannot be utilized","choices":["For the promotion of any particular religion","For the promotion of any particular business","Both as mentioned above","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Cultural and Educational Rights are also known as","choices":["Minority Rights","Majority Rights","Both as mentioned above","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Minorities have Right to","choices":["Establish and administer Educational institutions","Only to establish educational institutions","Carry on profession or business","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Minorities under Article 30 are based on","choices":["Religion or language","Religion only","Language only","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"___is the custodian of Fundamental Rights","choices":["Supreme Court & High Court","Civil Courts","President of India","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The Supreme Court is situated at","choices":["New Delhi","Mumbai","Bangalore","Kolkata"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The founding father of the Indian Constitution is","choices":["Dr.B.R.Ambekar","Gandhiji","Pandit Nehru","Sardar Valabhai Patel"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Supreme Court has power to issue _____ Kinds of writs","choices":["3","4","5","6"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Habeas Corpus means","choices":["You may have the body","What is your authority","Arrest the person","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who can apply for Habeas Corpus Writ?","choices":["The person arrested only","Any friend/relative of an arrested person","The police officer","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Mandamus means","choices":["Command","Request","Permission","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Mandamus writ lies against","choices":["Public authority","Private persons","Both as mentioned above","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Writ of Prohibition is issued against","choices":["Inferior Court","Tribunal","Both as mentioned above","Superior court"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Certiorari  means","choices":["To certify","To produce a person illegally arrested","Command","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"'Quo-Warranto' means","choices":["What is your authority","Direction","Issuina warrant","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"'Locus Standi' means","choices":["Right to move the Supreme Court/High Court","Right to be defended","Local authority","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Supreme Court has invented a new doctrine called","choices":["Public Interest Litigation","Private Interest Litigation","Publicity Interest Litigation","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Right to Education is contained in Article","choices":["Article 20","Article 21","Article 21A","Article 32"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Right to property is a","choices":["Fundamental Right","Legal Right","Mortal Right","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Right to start a business under Article 19 (1)(g) includes","choices":["Right not to close down the business","Right to close down the business","Right to travel abroad","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The number of Articles in the Constitution presently is","choices":["368","395","400","447"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Directive Principles of State Policy are contained in which part of the Constitution?","choices":["Part I","Part III","Part IV","Part-II"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The underlying objective of the Directive Principles is to achieve","choices":["Welfare State","police State","Secular State","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"There is right to adequate means of livelihood guaranteed to","choices":["Both men & women equally","men only","Women only","either men or to women"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"'Equal Pay for Equal Work' is an accompaniment of","choices":["Right to freedom","Right to equality","Right to freedom of religion","Right to constitutional remedies"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The Directive Principles of State Policy","choices":["Can be enforced in any court","Cab be enforced in High Court","Cannot be enforced in any Court","can be enforced only in the Supreme Court"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The Directive Principles of State Policy to be followed by the State for securing economic justice does not include","choices":["equal pay for equal work","to secure uniform civil code","equal right of men & women to adequate means of livelihood","to protect health & strength of workers"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Sexual harassment of working women is violation of","choices":["Fundamental duty","Fundamental right","Directive Principles of State Policy","Rule of law"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"This Act was not passed for implementing Directive Principles of State Policy","choices":["Forest Act","Maternity Benefit Act","Water Pollution Act","Arms Act"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Directive Principles of State Policy are","choices":["Political rights","Social rights","Constitutional rights","Legal rights"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"This is not a Directive Principle of State Policy","choices":["Living wage for workers","Right to work, education","Secure just & corrupt free judiciary","Participation of workers in management of Industries"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Uniform Civil Code means","choices":["Uniform Civil Procedure Code","Civil law applicable to common man","Common civil law applicable to all","Civil law applicable to Hindu Women & Muslim Women"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Free & Compulsory education for all children is provided under Article 45 until they attain the age of","choices":["14 years","21 years","18 years","16 years"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Equal justice & free aid is guaranteed to","choices":["Socially backward classes","Economically backward classes","Socially & economically backward classes","Educationally backward classes"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"State should protect every monument or place or object declared to be of","choices":["State importance","National importance","International importance","Local importance"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"State should take steps to separate","choices":["Judiciary from Executive","Legislature from Executive","Judiciary from Legislature","All the 3 organs from each other"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The object of organizing Village Panchayats is to introduce","choices":["Democracy at grass-root level","Indirect democracy","Aristocracy","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Fundamental Rights and Directive Principles are","choices":["unrelated to each other","Supplementary & Complementary","Opposed to each other","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Part-IV (A) consists of ____ fundamental duties","choices":["10","9","11","12"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Part-IV (A) was added to the Constitution in the year","choices":["1950","1972","1978","1976"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"For the violation of fundamental duties, an action","choices":["can be initiated in any court","can be initiated in the magistrate court","cannot be initiated in any court","can be initiated either in High Court or in Supreme court"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The Remedy available for breach of Fundamental Duties under the Constitution is","choices":["filing civil suit","filing criminal complaint","no remedy","filing Writ Petition"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Fundamental Duty demands","choices":["To work sincerely & respect the right of others","To abide by the Constitution","To prevent corruption","To abide by ethical values"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Which of the following is not a fundamental duty","choices":["to protect & improve natural environment","not to practice corruption","to develop scientific temper","to abide by Constitution"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The recent fundamental duty is","choices":["Duty of a parent or guardian to provide education to his child","Duty to safeguard public property","Duty to protect & improve the natural environment","Duty to abide by the Constitution"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Fundamental duties in the Constitution are addressed to the","choices":["Politicians","People","Workers","Students"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The Directive Principles of State Policy are in the form of","choices":["Rights","duties","Direction to state","obligation citizens"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The Constitution makers have borrowed the Directive Principles from","choices":["Constitution of Spain","Constitution of U.K.","Constitution of U.S.A","Constitution of Ireland"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The Directive Principles of State Policy are the obligations of","choices":["Central Govt.","State Govt.","Central & State Govt.","Citizen of India"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Article 37 of the constitution declares that the Directive Principles are","choices":["Enforceable in a court of law","Unenforceable","Enforceable only","None of them"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Article 38 of the Constitution aims to achieve","choices":["Social Justice","Economic Justice","Political Justice","All of the above"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The State is required to direct its policy towards securing equal right to a adequate means of livelihood for","choices":["Disabled persons","Men only","Women","Both men and Women"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"In Child Labour Abolition case the Supreme Court has held that the children below the age of ____ cannot be employed in any hazardous industry","choices":["16 years","18 years","21 years","14 years"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The Parliament of India has enacted ___ for the enforcement of Article 39(d)","choices":["Child labour Abolition Act","Equal remuneration Act","Protect of Human Rights Act","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Equal justice and free legal aid under the Social Security Charter has to be provided to","choices":["Socially backward classes","Economically backward classes","Politically backward","All of the above"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Now, free legal aid and speedy trial are","choices":["Only directives","Duty of the citizens","Fundamental rights","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"State has been directed to provide employment, education & public assistance in cases of unemployment for the unemployed, aged, sick and disabled","choices":["Irrespective of economic capacity of the nation","Out of the borrowings","Out of Consolidated Fund","Within the economic capacity of the state"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Living wage means","choices":["Minimum wage","Bare necessitates of life","Provision for education and insurance","Education & insurance etc. including the necessities of life"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Provision for care & education to children has been inserted as a Fundamental Right under","choices":["Article 21","Article 20","Article 21(A)","Article 31(A)"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Education below the age of 14 years is inserted as a fundamental right by","choices":["42nd Amendment","44th Amendment","85th Amendment","86th Amendment"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The Directive Principles under Article 46 considered ___ as educationally & economically backward/weaker sections of the society","choices":["Women & children","Disabled","SCs and STs","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"To protect and improve the natural environment and wild life is one of","choices":["Fundamental Rights","National policy","Directive Principles","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Article 48 of the Constitution directs the state to take steps to organize","choices":["Agriculture sector","Animal husbandry","both as mentioned above ","Scientific and technological advancement"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Monuments and places and objects of national importance are protected because India is a country with","choices":["Richest population","Lengthiest Constitution","Rich cultural heritage","Diverse culture"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The Directive Principle in Art.53 for promotion of international peace and Security became justifiable by","choices":["Universal Declaration of Human Rights, 1948","Protection of Human Rights Act, 1993","The Equal Remuneration Act 1976","All of the mentioned above"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Democracy at the grass root level is strengthened by","choices":["Municipalities","State legislatures","Village panchayats","Central government"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The fundamental rights and directive principles are","choices":["conflicting with each other","unrelated to each other","complement & supplement to each other","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Who is known as the first citizen of India?","choices":["The President","Prime Minister","Speaker","Chief Election Commissioner"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who is the Head of the State?","choices":["Governor","Prime Minister","President","Vice-President"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Who is the Head of the Executive?","choices":["A Cabinet","Cabinet headed by the Prime Minister","President","Speaker"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who is the Nominal Head of the Executive?","choices":["A Prime Minister","Vice-President","President","Governor"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"How much age is required by a person, to contest in the Presidential Election?","choices":["30+","32+","33+","35+"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Name the group, which is created for the election of the President?","choices":["Electoral College","Elected College","Electoral Commission","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who are the members of the Electoral College?","choices":["Elected members of both Houses of Parliament & elected MLA's","Almost all members of Parliament","Members of Parliament of Lok Sabha","Members of Parliament of Rajya Sabha"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"What kind of system of voting followed in President's election?","choices":["A open ballot system","Voting by oral announcement","Secret ballot system","Partial ballot system"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Who has to take an oath of the Person who won in the President's election?","choices":["Outgoing President","Chief Justice of India","Prime Minister","Governor"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"What is the term of the office of the president?","choices":["4 years","5 years","6 years","2 years"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"What is the maximum period for election of the President, if Vacancy is raised due to the death, resignation or removal of the President?","choices":["within 1 year","within 1 and a half years","within 6 months","within 2 months"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Name the bill or motion aimed to remove the President?","choices":["Impeachment Motion","no-confidence motion","Judgment of the Supreme Court","Majority approval of the Parliament"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who is the authorized person to remove the President after the Impeach Motion is passed in Parliament?","choices":["Chief Justice of India","Vice-President","Prime Minister","Parliament"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who can be appointed by the President as the P.M.?","choices":["Leader of the majority party in the Rajya Sabha","Leader of the party in the Lok Sabha","Leader of the majority party in LokaSabha","Leader of the opposition party in the Rajya Sabha"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"How does the appointment of Council of Ministers take place?","choices":["Appointed by the Prime Minister","By the President","By the President on the advice of the P.M","By the P.M on the advice of the President"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Who is the Supreme Commander of the defence forces of India?","choices":["Prime Minister","Parliament","Chief Justice of S.C.","The President"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Who Can control or regulate the exercise of military powers of the President?","choices":["Constitution","Parliament","Prime Minister","President"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Is the President a part of the Parliament?","choices":["No","Yes","Upto 3 years of the term","Upto 1 year of the term"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who can dissolve the Lok Sabha?","choices":["The President","Prime Minister","Supreme Court","Speaker of Lok Sabha"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Can the President withhold an Ordinary Bill?","choices":["No","Yes","Can withhold upto 6 months","upto 1 year"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"What is the total strength of the Rajya Sabha?","choices":["50","225","250","238"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"What is the life of the ordinance from the date of commencement of the sessions of the Parliament?","choices":["one year","nine months","six months","six weeks"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Who has the power to declare emergency?","choices":["Parliament","President","Prime Minister","Supreme Court"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Which Article empowers the President to impose National Emergency?","choices":["356","360","352","359"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Which Article empowers the President to impose State Emergency?","choices":["356","357","358","359"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Which Article empowers the President to impose Financial Emergency?","choices":["361","362","363","360"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"At what occasion President can impose National Emergency?","choices":["During internal rebellion","War","War & armed rebellion","During constitutional crisis"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"At what occasion the President can impose a State Emergency?","choices":["Failure of the State Government to rule as per the Constitution","Failure of the state Government to rule as per the Supreme Court","Failure of the state Government to rule as per the High Court","Failure of the state Government to rule as per the Governor"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who can become the Prime Minister?","choices":["Leader of the opposition party is Lok Sabha","The leader of the majority political party in the Lok Sabha","Leader of the Ruling Party","Leaders of both houses"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Can the President appoint other ministers without the advice of the PM?","choices":["No","Only the ministers can be appointed","Yes","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"What is the main hurdle to be crossed by the ruling party after being invited by the President to form the Government?","choices":["Cabinet should prove their majority in the Lok Sabha within the stipulated time given by the President","Should prove majority in the Rajya Sabha","Should prove the Majority in S.C.","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Can the PM advise the President to appoint a non-MP as a Minister?","choices":["No","Advise the speaker","Advise the Parliament","Yes"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"For how much period a non-MP can be allowed as minister?","choices":["3 months","Six months","9 Months","12 months"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"What condition has to be fulfilled if a non-MP to continue as a minister?","choices":["He has to elect as a member of Parliament within six months failing which he has to resign his post","to become MP in 3 months","within one year","no time limit"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Can a non-MP be continued as a minister without being elected?","choices":["No such rule","No","Yes","None"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who can allot and transfer the portfolios to the ministers?","choices":["The Prime Minister","The President","Parliament","Cabinet"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who is the authorized person to remove the ministers at anytime?","choices":["Advising the speaker","By advising the vice-president","Prime Minister by advising the president","By advising cabinet"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Who can supervise and control the business of the administration?","choices":["The Prime Minister","Cabinet","President","Supreme Court"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who can conduct and postpone the cabinet meetings?","choices":["Speaker","Parliament","The President","The PM"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Union Legislature of India is know as","choices":["Electoral body","The Parliament","Diet","Congress"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"How many Houses are there in parliament?","choices":["Five","Two","Three","Four"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Which Houses of Parliament represents Federal features?","choices":["Rajya Sabha","Lok Sabha","Vidhana Sabha","Vidhana Parishad"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"What kind of elections takes place to Rajya Sabha?","choices":["Direct elections","Indirect election","by-elections","mid-term election"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"If people's representatives, participate in the elections it is known as","choices":["Direct elections","Indirect elections","by-election","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"How many parts does the Parliament consists? What are those?","choices":["Two parts Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha","4 parts Lok Sabha, Rajya Sabha, Speaker & President","One members of Parliament","Three- Lok Sabha, Rajya Sabha, and the President"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Which is the powerful House of Parliament?","choices":["Rajya Sabha","Lok Sabha","President","Prime Minister"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Is the President an integral part of Parliament?","choices":["Yes","No","to some extent Yes","to some extent No"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"How does the Lok Sabha form?","choices":["Indirect","On the basis of the direct elections","No elections","Nomination"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"How many MPs to Lok Sabha are elected directly by the States of the nation?","choices":["545","540","525","500"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"How many members from the Union Territories are elected to the Lok Sabha?","choices":["50","30","25","20"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"What is the maximum strength of the Lok Sabha?","choices":["552","425","545","560"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"What is the term of the Lok Sabha?","choices":["2 years","6 years","4 years","5 years"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"When does the normal time of Lok Sabha extend?","choices":["Civil war","War","During the emergency","floods"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Name the elections take place for the whole Lok Sabha before its expiry?","choices":["Indirect elections","Mid-term elections","General elections","Bi-elections"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Name the elections take place for a few vacancies of Lok Sabha before the expiry of the term?","choices":["Direct","Indirect elections","None of these","Bi-elections"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"For how much period the term of Lok Sabha can be extended during emergency?","choices":["One year","Six months","Two years","Three years"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Within which time the elections should be conducted to the Lok Sabha after the Emergency is ceased to operate?","choices":["12 months","within 6 months","3 months","9 months"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Is there any educational qualification for becoming MP?","choices":["some qualification","yes","No","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"For how much period mid term election are conducted?","choices":["5 years","3 years","4 years","2 years"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The required age to contest in the election of the Lok Sabha is","choices":["Below 25 years","30 years","25 years+","35 year"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Who is the Presiding officer of the Lower House of Parliament?","choices":["Vice-president","Speaker","Prime Minister","President"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Can the Speaker continue in his post after loosing membership in the House?","choices":["Yes after SC permission","No","Yes","don't know"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who will elect the Speaker of the Lower House?","choices":["President","Members of the Lower House","Prime Minister","Vice-president"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who will act as Speaker in his absence?","choices":["Vice-President","Defence Minister","Home Minister","Deputy Speaker"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"How is the Speaker removed?","choices":["by the President","By the Prime Minister","By the Parliament","When the Lower House passes a resolution by an absolute majority after a notice is issued 14 days in advance for such removal before passing of resolution by the President"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"If any member elected as a Speaker, can be continue in his political party?","choices":["yes","By the permission of the SC, he can continue","None of these","No, He should resign his political party"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"How many kinds of Bill are there?","choices":["Three kinds","One kind","Two kinds","five kinds"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"If the Bill is introduced by opposition and independent MP, it is known as","choices":["Private Bill","Public Bill","Official Bill","Non-Official Bill"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"If the Bill introduced by the ruling party MP it is known as","choices":["Act","law","Private Bill","Public Bill"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"How many 'Readings' a Bill has to cross in each House to get passed?","choices":["Two","Four","Five","Three"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"If Legislature has only one House, it is know as","choices":["Mono-cameralism","Cameralism","Bi-cameralism","Uni-cameralism"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"What kind of majority does an Ordinary Bill require to pass in Parliament?","choices":["Special majority","Absolute majority","Simple majority","Overwhelming majority"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"What is the purpose of the Joint Session of the Parliament?","choices":["to pass the budget","to elect the speaker","to remove the president","to resolve the deadlock between the two houses"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Annual statement of income and expenditure of the Government is know as","choices":["Agenda","Catalogue","Calender","Budget"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Who will present the Budget in the month of March every in the Lok Sabha?","choices":["Finance Minister","Prime Minister","Home Minister","Speaker"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Can the Money Bill be rejected by the President when comes second time after reconsideration by the Lower House with or without modification","choices":["Yes","No, it has to be signed by the President","His will & wish","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Name the highest or apex court of India?","choices":["Federal Court","Lok-adalath","Supreme Court","International Court"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"How is the supremacy of the Constitution safeguarded?","choices":["by independent and impartial Judiciary","by the parliament","by the cabinet","press"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"What is the total strength of the Supreme Court?","choices":["30","Twenty Five Judges and One Chief Justice together Twenty-Six","35","29"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who does appoint the Judges of the Supreme Court?","choices":["Cabinet","President on his own","President appoints the Judges after consulting the Chief Justice of India","President by consulting Prime Minister"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Who does appoint Chief Justice of the Supreme Court?","choices":["By the President","By the Prime Minister","By the cabinet","By the Speaker of Lok Sabha"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Is the President bound to any one of the appointment of the Chief Justice of India?","choices":["Yes","Bound to the advice of the Parliament","None of these","No"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"What is the retirement age of the Chief Justice and Judges of the Supreme Court?","choices":["62 years","60 years","65 years","58 years"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Name the process through which Judges of the Supreme Court and High Court are removed?","choices":["No-confidence motion","By order of the Speaker","By order of the Prime Minister","Through impeachment Motion"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"On what grounds the Judges are removed?","choices":["Failed to give effective Judgment","Proved misbehavior, incapacity","Absconding from duty","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"What is the present salary of the Chief Justice of India?","choices":["Rs. 1,33,000","Rs. 1,00,000/-","Rs. 1,35,000/-","Rs. 1,34,000/-"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"What is the salary of the Supreme Court Judges of India?","choices":["Rs.90,000/-","Rs.1,22,000/-","Rs.1,26,000/-","Rs.1,30,000/-"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The jurisdiction exercised by the Supreme Court to deal the cases related to the powers of the Centre and States is known as","choices":["Appellate Jurisdiction","Original Jurisdiction","Advisory Jurisdiction","Special Jurisdiction"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Name the jurisdiction exercised by the Courts to deal the cases come from the subordinate courts?","choices":["Appellate Jurisdiction","Constitutional Jurisdiction","Original Jurisdiction","Judicial activism"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Under what jurisdiction, the cases involving the interpretation of the Constitution, are dealt by the Supreme Court?","choices":["Original Jurisdiction","Special Jurisdiction","Appellate Jurisdiction","Advisory Jurisdiction"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Name the Article, empowering the Supreme Court to issue writs for the enforcement of FRs?","choices":["Under Article 32","Under Article 33","Under Article 35","Under Article 40"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Name the jurisdiction exercised by the Supreme Court to give or not to give advices to the President whenever the later asked on the matter related to public issue?","choices":["Original Jurisdiction","Appellate Jurisdiction","Lok adalath","Advisory Jurisdiction"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Not obeying the judgment of the Supreme Court is know as","choices":["Insulting the Court","Disrespecting the Court","Contempt of Court","Dishonouring the Court"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The power of the Supreme Court to examine the Constitutional validity of the laws of the Central and State Governments is known as","choices":["Judicial Authority","Judicial Review","Judicial Activism","Judicial Remand"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who can decide the election disputes of President and Vice-President of India?","choices":["High court","Parliament","Supreme Court","Executive"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Is the Supreme Court bound by its own judgment?","choices":["No","Yes","Bound to some extent","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"What is required for the Supreme Court to deliver impartial judgments?","choices":["Independent constitution","Govt's interference","Free from political control","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2}]